Guide to the Charles Gilbert Spross Papers, 1907-1982
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Charles Gilbert Spross Papers
1907-1982
Spross, Charles Gilbert
1 cubic foot (3 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Drafts of sheet music, scrapbooks, and biographical ephemera related to Charles Gilbert Spross's career as a pianist, accompanist, and composer.
Biographical Note
Charles Gilbert Spross (1874-1961) was a pianist, accompanist, and composer. He was born in Poughkeepsie, New York, studied under Franz Xavier Scharwenke and Carl V. Lachmund, and traveled the world to accompany a number of opera singers, violinists, and other musicians.
Scope and Content Note
Drafts of sheet music, scrapbooks, and biographical ephemera related to Charles Gilbert Spross's career as a pianist, accompanist, and composer.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Subjects:
Composers--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Pianists--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Musicians--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie
Document Types:
Clippings (information artifacts); Printed ephemera; Scrapbooks; Sheet music
VCL Categories:
Music
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, February 2011. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, February 2023.
Acquisition Information
The scrapbooks and most of the sheet music were a gift of R. Philip Hart, 2010 [M2011-011]. Additional material was transfered from the Vassar College Music Library in 2010 [M2010-011]. A gift of seven pieces of sheet music came from the New England Conservatory in 2015. Additional sheet music and ephemera were a gift of James F. Eilers, Jr. in 2023 [M2023-006].
Container List
- Award, "A Citation of Honor to Charles Gilbert Spross, Music Director," First Congregational Church, Poughkeepsie, NY, 1955 May 1 (Folder 1.01)
- Clippings about Charles Gilbert Spross, undated; [photocopies] (Folder 2.01)
- Printed ephemera and programs, 1982 (Folder 1.02)
- Scrapbook, 1907-1975 (Box 3)
- Scrapbook, 1911-1961 (Box 3)
- Sheet Music - Autograph Manuscript
  - Hart, Gertrude Spross, "Whimsies", 1938 February (Folder 1.03)
  - Puccini, Giacomo, "La Tosca," [arranged?] by Charles Gilbert Spross, undated (Folder 2.02)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "I Will Extol Thee, O' Lord," sacred duet for soprano and tenor, undated (Folder 2.03)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Invocation to Life", undated (Folder 1.04)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Invocation to Life," for violin, viola, and cello, undated (Folder 2.04)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Let All My Life Be Music", undated (Folder 1.05)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Lorraine, Lorraine, Lorrée", undated (Folder 1.06)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Non [Nobis?] Dominé, 1.) accompaniment", undated (Folder 1.07)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Polacca Brilliante (for 2 pianos)", undated (Folder 2.05)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Thy Will Be Done" / "I Will Life Up Mine Eyes" / "Blow Ye the Trumpet in Lion" / "Like As the Hart" [2 drafts], undated (Folder 1.08)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Yesterday and Today", circa 1932 (Folder 1.09)
- Sheet Music - Published
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Ask Me No More," Cincinnati: The John Church Company, undated (Folder 2.06)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "The Day is Done," Cincinnati: The John Church Company, circa 1914 (Folder 1.10)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Invocation to Life," Philadelphia: Theodore Presser Co., circa 1930 (Folder 1.11)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Let All My Life Be Music," Philadelphia: The John Church Company, undated (Folder 2.06)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Minor and Major," Cincinnati: The John Church Company, circa 1920 (Folder 1.12)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Minor and Major," Cincinnati: The John Church Company, 1926 February, undated (Folder 2.07)
    Note: Annotated by Spross and dedicated to soprano Genia Zielinska. Includes printed ephemera about Zielinska.
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Through a Primrose Dell," Cincinnati: The John Church Company, circa 1910 (Folder 2.06)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Will O' the Wisp," Cincinnati: The John Church Company, circa 1909; [2 copies] (Folder 2.06)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "The Wind" / "Living and Dying" / "Love Planted My Rose," Cincinnati: The John Church Company, circa 1907 (Folder 2.06)
  - Spross, Charles Gilbert, "Yesterday and Today," Philadelphia: The John Church Company, circa 1908 (Folder 2.06)